{
  "reference_number": "11429",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "2050 is too late. We need a zero emissions target in legislation now but with an earlier date for achievement."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "All green house gas emissions should be included. The target date should be much earlier. (When we talk about short-lived\n methane, we need to remember that it breaks down into long-lived CO2.)"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Emissions trading is misguided. It is pushed by fossil fuel industries because it allows them to continue with their profitable\n\n businesses while giving the illusion that money can clean up the mess. The only solution is to stop producing the gases. I quote\n George Marshall's book, Don't even think about it: \"Emissions trading turned out to be a mechanism of byzantine complexity that\n distributed responsibility and severed the connection between personal behaviour and moral responsibility. With trading, it made no\n\n difference whether you flew or drove or whether you bought electricity from a wind farm or a coal plant - the emissions had already\n been decided and allocated as permits. Nor did it even work. .... By 2013 polluters had banked so many cut-price permits that they\n\n could expand emissions enough to outweigh the savings of all the European renewable and energy efficiency efforts combined.\"\n (p165) Rather than carbon trading, we need to prevent emissions from happening in the first place, using regulation, taxation and\n rationing."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Kind of a silly question. At some point, it's going to become impossible for even the most blinkered to ignore the floods, fires and\n\n crop failures that already pepper the evening news bulletin, and there will be public pressure to reduce emissions more rapidly, at\n which point the target date would be changed anyway."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Smacks of carbon trading thinking. If you set a budget, you'll use all of it. I don't see how setting budgets sends the right message\n about the urgency of reducing emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "see above - budgets are a bad idea."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "What about health and equity? There is far too much emphasis on protecting businesses and profits. You don't seem to get how\n\nurgent and dangerous climate change is."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The only budget should be zero emissions, and the target should be well before 2050."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The Commission should be a decision-making body, not just advisory."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "And if they've got any brains, they will decide that emissions trading schemes are not fit for purpose, abolish the NZETS and adopt\nregulation, taxation and rationing to reduce fossil fuel use."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "You have no public health expertise in there. This is pretty important. Also you don't have professional communication expertise. We\n\nall know that scientific language does not adequately communicate to the general public about climate change. Clear, engaging\ncommunication is vital."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There are some very large issues to be resolved around how we deal with the uneven impact of climate change (eg what do we do\nabout uninsurable/lost housing around coasts, massive changes in the economy such major as downscaling of the aviation industry,\n\nsupporting farmers to switch away from animal agriculture, possibly food rationing, certainly fossil fuel rationing, accepting large\ninflows of refugees). The language of the proposal suggests that planning for adaptation will mean we deal with it OK. I think we will\nactually see a complete breakdown of society."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I strongly support climate change legislation. I think the approach is a bit \"this is how we do things\" and failing to recognise that\nclimate change is not a standard issue problem. The discussion document reads as if the writers don't really appreciate the urgency\n\nof the problem. The drafters should all be made to read George Marshall's excellent book."
    }
  ]
}
